Finding Aid for the Byron McAfee Papers LSC.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
Byron McAfee collection of papers relating to the Nahuatl language
circa 1553-1964
UCLA Library Special Collections
McAfee, Byron
LSC.0339
9.5 Linear Feet (19 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Byron McAfee (1883-1966) was an American-born ethnohistorian and linguist who studied Nahua language and culture in Mexico. The collection consists of McAfee's research papers and original manuscripts from Mexico's colonial period.
Restrictions on Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Material in the boxes 1-2 contain microfilmed material are in nitrate storage and are unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942333863606533
Biography
McAfee was born in Houston, Texas, in 1883; emigrated to Mexico in 1906 as employee of the Compañía Mexicana de Peteo El Aguila, S.A.; began studying the Nahuatl language in 1907 under John H. Cornyn with whom he jointly authored several studies; after Cornyn's death in 1941, McAfee collaborated with Angel María Garibay K. and Robert H. Barlow; became an acknowledged expert in Nahuatl studies and published widely.
Expanded Biographical Narrative
Byron McAfee (1883-1966) was born in Houston, Texas, and emigrated to Mexico in 1906 as an employee of the Compañía de Petróleos El Aguila. Shortly thereafter, he joined a Nahuatl study group at the Benjamin Franklin Library in Mexico City where he made contacts with scholars such as Robert Barlow, Miguel Leon Portilla, John H. Cornyn and Doña Luz Jimenez (a noted native Nahuatl consultant, also known as Julia Jimenez Gonzalez). McAfee became known as a prolific ethnohistorian and Nahuatl linguist through his research collaborations with Cornyn, and publications of several studies. After Cornyn's death in 1941, McAfee collaborated with noted scholars such as Angel María Garibay K. and Robert H. Barlow, and maintained friendships with Mexican intellectuals such as Alfonso Caso and Manuel Gamio.
McAfee's publications include: The Techialoyan Codex E (Codex Cempoala, Hidalgo, 1945), La Danza de la Gran Conquista (translation, 1952), Tlacahuapahualistli (with Cornyn, 1943), The Titles of Tezcotzingo (with Barlow, 1945), and The Techialoan Codices: Codex K (1946), in Tlalocan; Anales de la Conquista de Tlatelolco 1473 a 1521 (with Barlow, 1945), La Guerra Entre Tlatelolco y Tenochtitlan Según el Códice Cozcatzin (1946) and Unos Anales Coloniales de Tlatelolco, 1519-1633 (1948), in Tlatelolco a Través de los Tiempos; Diccionario de Elementos Fonéticos en Escritura Jeroglífica (Códice Mendocino) (1949) and El Códice de Mixtepec (with Garibay, 1949); The Techialoyan Codex of Tepotzotlan: Codex X (Reylands Mexican Manuscript l) in Bulletin of the John Ryland Library (with Donald Robertson, 1960).
Scope and Content
The microfilm checklist is a revision of an earlier draft compiled in February, 1974, and replaces the earlier version since it reflects the organization of the Collection developed in January-February, 1978. This list, as the first, is a working draft and remains incomplete. Lacunae include several reels of microfilm and the collection of colonial period Nahuatl manuscripts.
Sixteen of these manuscripts were published in Beyond the Codices: The Nahua View of Colonial Mexico, University of California Press, 1976, edited and translated by Arthur J.O. Anderson, Frances Berdan and James Lockhart.
An inventory of the materials sent by Cornyn to the University of Toronto (see Box 9, item 1) is appended to the checklist. It is intended that the inventory of the Collection will soon be completed and then expanded into a more substantive study.
Most of this collection is in Nahuatl and German with portions in Spanish and English.
Expanded Scope and Content
The collection consists of Byron McAfee's research papers (microfilm and typescripts) and original manuscripts from Mexico's colonial period. The research papers contain drafts of translations and essays by McAfee and his major collaborator, John Hubert Cornyn, on a variety of subjects including colonial codices, Spanish-Nahuatl dictionaries and vocabularies, and Nahua history and culture. The papers also include printed instructional and linguistic materials on Nahuatl, such as an 1887 Nahuatl grammar from Mexico; full transcriptions of important 16th century works by friars Bernardino de Sahagún, Alonso de Molina and Andres de Olmos; translations and linguistic studies of Nahuatl dramas; and material extracted from Mexican political and social movements related to Nahua studies. (Published works have been included in the finding aid; in addition, full catalog records for these books can be found in the UCLA Library online catalog by performing a keyword search on the phrase, "Byron McAfee papers" in the UCLA Library catalog.)
The manuscripts series of the collection consists of testaments, deeds, petitions, complaints, and contracts for the sale of land from the areas of Metepec, Azcapotzalco, Tlaxcala and Coyoacan, dating from 1553 to 1864. These manuscripts, chiefly in Nahuatl, document the everyday activities and property holdings of men and women under Spanish colonial rule. Fourteen of the manuscripts in Series 3 were published in Beyond the Codices: the Nahua View of Colonial Mexico, which was edited and translated by Arthur J.O. Anderson, Frances Berdan and James Lockhart and published by the University of California Press, 1976.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Microfilm, 1565-1941 (2 boxes). In nitrate storage and therefore UNAVAILABLE FOR USE.
Research papers, 1768-1964 (16 boxes), subseries A-E as follows:
Codex studies, 1857-1961 (4 boxes).
Dictionaries and language, 1884-1956 (5 boxes).
John Hubert Cornyn papers, 1926-1930 (2 boxes).
Nahua history and culture, 1857-1964 (3 boxes).
Miscellaneous, 1768-1953 (2 boxes).
Manuscripts, 1553-1864 (1 box).
Separated Material
Cornyn Manuscripts sent to the University of Toronto 1937-38
Missing Title
1. Souls and Testamentary Executors (English translation from Aztec).
2. The Judgment Day--Aztec Text--English Translation.
3. Ixcit Cheel--Maya Text--English Translation.
4. Catechismo Breve--Typescript.
5. Cartilla o Silabario--Aztec--Typescript.
6. Buried Cities of Mexico--Manuscript.
21. Compendio de Gramatica Nahuatl--Luna Cardenas Manuscript.
24. Sacrifice of Isaac (Aztec comedy)--Cornyn Manuscript.
28. Relación Morcuriana--Typewritten.
31. The four Suns (translated from Aztec)--Cornyn translation.
32. The Rape of Fire (from Aztec)--Cornyn.
33. The Merchant (Aztec comedy)--Cornyn translation.
35. Coyotl Ixtlamatqui (The Wise Coyote)--Cornyn Manuscript.
36. Obregon's Administration Manuscript.
69. Bringing up Children--Aztec--English--Cornyn.
81. Bringing up Children (2nd manuscript).
92. In EzopoiZazanillatol (Aztec)--Hunt Cortes.
93. Song of Quetzalcoatl--(original manuscript)--Cornyn.
110. A Toltec Chronicle (Aztec)--Cornyn.
123. Coyotl ihuan Tlacuatzin (Aztec Folk Tale)--Cornyn.
124. El Perro Viejo y el Coyote (Aztec Folk Tale)--Cornyn.
126. Tlacuatzin ihuan Coyotl (Aztec Folk Tale)--Cornyn.
131. Aztec Proper names--Cornyn Manuscript.
132. Cacaton ihuan Quimichi--Cornyn Manuscript.
133. The four Winds--Cornyn Manuscript.
134. The Funeral Oration, Archbishop Diaz--Cornyn Manuscript.
173. Tlaloc (God of the Waters) and his Symbols--Manuscript.
174. In Animatzin ihuan Albaceas and translation. J.H. Cornyn.
198. Analysis of a Fable in Aztec--Cornyn Manuscript.
199. Indian Names on the Laredo-Mexico Highway--Manuscript.
200. Tlatlatlauhtilteacuicayotl (Aztec) Jesus Valencia Cuauhtla Manuscript.
201. Grammatical Analysis of an Aztec Text--Manuscript.
208. Funeral Oration. Spanish-Aztec--Escalada Manuscript.
209. The Aztec Linguistic Field--Cornyn.
Manuscripts, Nahuatl -- Specimens.; Mexico -- History -- Spanish colony, 1540-1810 -- Archives.; Mexico -- History -- Conquest, 1519-1540 -- Archives.; Nahuas -- History -- Archives.; Nahuas -- Social life and customs -- Archives.; Nahuatl language -- Archives.; Historians -- United States -- Archives.; Historians -- Mexico -- Archives.; Linguists -- Mexico -- Archives.; Linguists -- United States -- Archives.; Cornyn, John Hubert; McAfee, Byron -- Archives
- I. Microfilm (incomplete inventory)., 1565-1941. (Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  18 reels of microfilm. Images include copies of McAfee's research materials and Mexican manuscripts. Microfilm boxes are in nitrate storage.
  - Eduard Seler:
    - Einiges über die Naturlischen Gründlagen Mexikanischer Mythen.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.3, pp.305-351., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Les Ruines de Mitla.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.3, pp.470-486., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Die Wandskulpturen in Tempel des Pulquegottes von Tepoztlan.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.3, pp.487-513., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Aztlan, die Heimat der Azteken.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.2, pp.31-48., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Ueber die Worte Anauac und Nahuatl.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.2, pp.49-77., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Altmexikanischer Schmuck und Sociale und Militarische Rangabzeichen.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.2, pp.509-619., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Die Teotiuacan-Kultur des Hochlands von Mexico.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.5, pp.405-585., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Die Sage von Quetzalcouatl und Den Tolteken in den neuerer Zeit bekannt.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.5, pp.178-196., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Das Weltbild der alten Mexikaner.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.4, pp.3-167., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Das Mexikanische Land.Gesammelte Abhandlungen,, vol.4, pp.405-432., 1908. (Reel 1)
    - Códice Fernández-Leal (Peñafiel,)., 1895. (Reel 1)
    - Lienzo de Zacatepec y Mapa de Zacatepec (Peñafiel,)., 1895. (Reel 1)
    - Sahagún,Primeros Memoriales, Chapter 1-4 (Paso y Troncoso edition). (Reel 1)
    - Molina, Ordenanzas. Manuscript. Incomplete., 16th century. (Reel 1)
    - Mexikanischen Gamalde von Culuhtlantlingo (from Globus,, pp.352-354)., February 4, 1899. (Reel 1)
    - Frederick Starr,Mapa de Cuahutlantlingo (University of Chicago,)., 1898. (Reel 1)
    - Trabajo Presentado Ante el Primer Congreso Nacional de Ciencias Sociales, July 1941. (Reel 1)
  - Doctrina Xpiana breve y compendiosa por via de un diálogo entre un maestro y un discípulo, sacada en lengua castellana y mexicana ()., 1565. (Reel 2)
  - Reel 2
    - Juan de la Anunciación, Cathecismo en lengua mexicana y española ()., 1577. (Reel 2)
    - Sagrada escritura en Latino-Mexicano. Manuscript, Mexico (J.F. Ramírez, Manuscript number 507. Bancroft Library)., 17th century. 1880. (Reel 2)
    - Dominical en Mexicano. (National Library of Mexico. Manuscript number 15-4-32. (Reel 2)
    - Catecismo Hispano-Mexicano (). (Ramírez, Manuscript number 513. Bancroft Library)., 1714. 1880. (Reel 2)
    - Tratado espiritual. Neyononotzaloni ic mixuic moyolnonotza in tlaneltocanti inic monoma panahuic. (Reel 2)
    - S. Ignacio de Loyola la Compañía de Jesús. (Reel 2)
    - Probably (National Library of Mexico. Manuscript number 15-4-129, 147 pp.)., 18th century. (Reel 2)
  - Reel 3
    - Nahuatl document (undetermined identity). (Reel 3)
    - Atlas geográfico. (26 pp., from the Library of the Society of Mexico Geográfica y Estadistica. (Reel 3)
    - Nizcuitile--teatro religioso. (Manuscript in collection of Gómez de Orozco; 20 pp.)., 17th century. (Reel 3)
    - Ordenación, In Ramírez collection., 1629. (Reel 3)
    - Manuscript, siglo 16(?): Pueblo de Xanpetolo. (4 hojas and map; Bancroft Library). (Reel 3)
    - Maps (2) of the towns of Xan-petolo Ytlahuac (Bancroft Library). (Reel 3)
    - Narrative of. Firch and Pine. Nugget Press, 1941. (Reel 3)
    - Photos of library files and shelves (unidentified). (Reel 3)
    - Three exposures of an unidentified Nahuatl manuscript. (Reel 3)
  - Reel 4
    - Collection of Teotihuacan vessels (drawings). (Reel 4)
    - Molina dictionary, 1571 edition. (Reel 4)
    - Unidentified Mexican manuscripts (no. 85,115,237,301,378, 419). (Reel 4)
    - Codex Ixtlilxochitl. (Reel 4)
    - Unidentified manuscript (in Spanish). (Reel 4)
    - Collection of relaciones (dated from)., 1579-81. (Reel 4)
    - Anales of Chimalpahin (1889 edition). (Reel 4)
    - Codex Osuna (1878 edition). (Reel 4)
    - Anales of Puebla and Cholula. (Reel 4)
    - Papel de Hernan Cortés (Harvard University manuscript). (Reel 4)
    - Alonso de Molina,Ordinancia (Manuscript). (Reel 4)
    - Notes for Códice de Quiotepec. (Reel 4)
    - W. Jiménez Moreno,Estudio del Códice de Quiotepec.. (Reel 4)
    - Codex Franco Rodrigues Reyes. (Reel 4)
    - Illustration relating to pre-Hispanic Inca land cultivation. (Reel 4)
    - Mexican Manuscript (Berkeley, no. 93, ff. 226-254). (Reel 4)
  - Reel 7
    - Antiguedades Mexico, Manuscript con colores (colored)., 1827. (Reel 7)
    - Typewritten bibliography of Paul Radin., 3pp. (Reel 7)
    - Alonso de Molina,Vocabulario de la Lengua Mexicana (Leipzig,)., 1880. (Reel 7)
    - Genealogie de Zolin. Contains photos of 1827 Icazbalceta lithographs(?). (Reel 7)
  - Reel 8
    - Documentos relativos a la Sociedad Aquiles Jerdan. (Reel 8)
    - Queja elevada el Supremo Gobierno del Estado de Durango. (Reel 8)
    - Testimonio de la Sentencia del Supremo Tribunal de Justicia del Estado. (Reel 8)
    - Influencia de los Ingenieros y los Arquitectos en el Progreso Nacional ()., 1918. (Reel 8)
    - Maps of the world and Russia (27 exposures; in Russian). (Reel 8)
    - Biblioteca Nacional. Mexico Manuscript, Relating to the Mexican calendar, religious festivals of the Church., 1628. (Reel 8)
  - Reel 9
    - Padre Juan Antonio Balthasar, Sermoneo en Mexicano. Colegio de San Gregorio de Mexico. no. 15-4-122,(?)., 1735. (Reel 9)
    - Sermones en Mexica.(?). National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-124. 470 pp., 17th century. (Reel 9)
    - Sermones en Mexica. (Diego Marcos, supposed author;)., 1619. (Reel 9)
  - Reel 10
    - Miscelenea Sagrada en Mexicano.(?). (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-133)., 17th century. (Reel 10)
    - Consejos Misticos en Mexicano.(?). (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-128; 951 pp.)., 17th century. (Reel 10)
  - Reel 11
    - Origen de Cuitlhuac y Otros Documentos (copied by Chimalpopoca). Late (National Library of Mexico, no.14-2-64)., 16th century. (Reel 11)
    - Códice Aubin (; 1902 Mexican edition)., 1576. (Reel 11)
    - Alonso de Molina,Confesionario Mayor en la Lengua Mexicana y Castellana ()., 1569. (Reel 11)
    - Sermones en Mexicana () 111 folios., 1765. (Reel 11)
    - Códice Osuna (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-123; edition)., 1878. (Reel 11)
    - Anales de Tecamachalco. From Peñafiel, Colección de Documentos para la Historia Mexicana, 1903. (Reel 11)
    - Huehuetlatolli (Ramírez Catalog, Bancroft Library no.521)., 1880. (Reel 11)
    - Alonso de Molina,Doctrina Christiana en Lengva Castillana y Mexicana ()., 1578. (Reel 11)
  - Reel 12
    - Henri Saussure,Le Manuscrit du Cacique ()., 1892. (Reel 12)
    - 1770 plates from the Metrícula de Tributos. (Reel 12)
    - Facsimile edition of the Telleriano-Remensis (Hamy, 1899 edition). (Reel 12)
    - Alonso de Molina, Ordinancia. (J.F. Ramírez, Catalog no.538) Catalog cards only., 1880. (Reel 12)
    - Lope de la Vega, Tres Comedias (Bancroft Library; J.F. Ramírez, Catalog no.515)., 1880. (Reel 12)
    - Códice Laud (from Paso y Troncoso negatives). (Reel 12)
    - Códice Frejervery Meyer. (Reel 12)
    - Unidentified positives from the Gates Collection. (Reel 12)
    - Techialoyan Manuscript (Bancroft Library). (Reel 12)
    - Falsified Manuscript (Bancroft Library). (Reel 12)
    - Anales Tepanecas (Ramírez Catalog no.6). (Reel 12)
    - Anales Mexicanos ()., 1853. (Reel 12)
    - Códice de Anales Aztecas (National Museum of Mexico, no.35-9). (Reel 12)
    - Anales de los Mexicanos, Número 1., (22 ff.). (Reel 12)
    - Anales, Número 4 ()., 1570-1581. (Reel 12)
    - Anales, Número 5 ()., 1691-1701. (Reel 12)
    - Vuelta de la última hoja de los Anales an Lengva Mexicana, 1691-1701. (Reel 12)
      (Gómez de Orozco Colección de Anales Mexicanos, Número 5).
    - Códice de Anales Aztecas (National Museum of Mexico, no.35-9). (Reel 12)
    - Títulos de las tierras de los indios de Cuitlahuac. (Reel 12)
    - Anónimo Mexicano (from Anales del Museo Nacional, pp.115-31). (Reel 12)
    - Anales de Tiaxcala (Anales, no.2). (Reel 12)
    - Anales de Tepeaca (Anales, no.23). (Reel 12)
  - Reel 13
    - Positive of Reel #12. (Reel 13)
  - Reel 14
    - Parárolas de Saloman (including Liber Ecclesiates).Manuscript., 16th century. (Reel 14)
      General note
      (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-130, 391 pp.).
    - Santorial en Mexicano.(?). (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-132 bis, 236 folios)., 17th century. (Reel 14)
    - Epístolas en Mexico. (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-126; 332 pp.)., 16th century. (Reel 14)
  - Reel 15
    - Juan de la Anunciación, Sermonario en Lengva Mexicana (Antonio Ricardo,)., 1577. (Reel 15)
    - Sermones y Egemplos en Mexicano,(National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-117; 358 folios)., 16-17th century. (Reel 15)
    - Sermones en Mexicano.(?). (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-118; 330 pp.)., 17th century. (Reel 15)
  - Reel 16
    - Sermones en Mexicano. (National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-121; 263 pp.)., 17th or 18th century. (Reel 16)
    - Sermones en Mexicano.(National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-120; 326 pp.)., 17th or 18th century. (Reel 16)
    - Sermones en Mexicano.(National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-119; 808 pp.)., 17th century. (Reel 16)
  - Reel 17
    - Sermones en Mexicano.(National Library of Mexico, no.15-4-125; 407 folios.)., 17th century?. (Reel 17)
  - Reel 18
    - Fray Alonso de Molina,Ordenanzas (Ramírez Collection, Catalog no.538; Bancroft Library)., 1880. (Reel 18)
    - Fray Alonso de Molina,Ordenanzas. (in Soc. Mex. de Geo. y Est.)., Mid-16th century. (Reel 18)
    - Fray Alonso de Molina,De la Muerte de Tres Ni¯nas (copy in Bancroft Library). (Reel 18)
    - Manuscript Linguisticas C 41 (Bancroft Library). (Reel 18)
    - Mexico manuscript no.93 (Documentos Historicos sobre Durango, pp.207-229). (Reel 18)
    - Andrés de Olmos, El Arte de la Lengua Mexicana. (Anales Mexicanos, Núm. 3). (Reel 18)
    - Anales de Tlaxcala (Anales Mexicanos, Núm. 2). (Reel 18)
    - Anales de los Mexicanos, Núm. 1., (22 ff.). (Reel 18)
    - Versos de la Danca de la Gran Conquista, Entrada de Don Fernando Cortes (Collection of Mis. Bilder Christensen, Mexico; 33 pp.). (Reel 18)
    - Unindentified Spanish Manuscript. (Reel 18)
    - Alonzo de Zurita,Relación de la Nueva Espa¯na.copy. (National Library of Mexico, no.34-5-6-7-8)., 19th century. (Reel 18)
    - . Lista de Soldados (?). (Reel 18)
    - Transcription of Primeros Memoriales by Wigberto Jiménez Moreno. (Reel 18)
    - Idioma Nahuatl (; Chimalpopoca?)., 1869. (Reel 18)
    - Sahagún (essay by Eduard Seler, 251 pp.)., c. 1926. (Reel 18)
    - Horacio Carochi,Arte de la Lengua Mexicana. (202 pp.)., 1759;. (Reel 18)
    - Alonso de Molina,Vocabulario en Lengua Castellana y Mexicana ()., 1571. (Reel 18)
- II. Research papers, 1768-1964.; 16 boxes.
  Series II is divided into 5 topical subseries:
  IIA. Codex studies, 1857-1961 (4 boxes).
  IIB. Dictionaries and language, 1884-1956 (5 boxes).
  IIC. John Hubert Cornyn papers, 1926-1930 (2 boxes).
  IID. Nahua history and culture, 1857-1964 (3 boxes).
  IIE. Miscellaneous, 1768-1953 (2 boxes).
  - IIA. Codex studies, 1857-1961.; (4 boxes).
    Research papers and transcriptions related to the study of colonial codices, including the such as the Florentine Codex, Codex Borgia, Codice de Santa Maria and the Historia Tolteca Chichimeca. Materials are arranged alphabetacally by folder title.
    - Carrillo, Soledad Manzo. Tesis de Arqueología, 1934.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Undergraduate thesis by a student of Alfonso Caso. Compares Mixtec day glyphs with Mexica glyphs. Color images with handwritten notes. 39 leaves, bound with red string.
    - Leon, Nicolas. Observaciones del Padre Marquez Acerca del Calendario del Códice Mexicano del Cardenal Borgia, ca. 1936.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Published essay on the pre-Columbian calendar.
    - McAfee, Byron. Preliminary Checklist of Mesoamerican Pictorial Manuscripts in the Native Tradition ("Códice"), 1961.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Rough draft of an essay, "intended to correct, amplify and otherwise supersede the first preliminary Handbook of Middle American Indians checklist of Mesoamerican pictorial Manuscripts, issued in June 1960." Final page includes a note by H.B. Nicholson, dated August 25, 1961. Bound mimeograph.
    - Mena, Ramón. Educacion Intelectual y Fisica entre los Nahuas y Mayas Precolombinos., 1930.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Published in Mexico, [s.n.] On the physical and intellectual education of Pre- Columbian Mayas and Nahuas. Signed by the author.
    - México. Junta Colombina. Homenaje á Cristóbal Colón: antigüedades mexicanas., 1892.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Published in Mexico, by the Oficina Tipográfica de la Secretaria de Fomento. On Mexican manuscripts and codices.
    - Codex Aubin, 1857.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Spanish translation by Lic. Fausto Galicia of the original Nahuatl text. Typescript with holograph annotations.
    - Escritura Jeroglifica Mexica, 1948.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Published in Mexico, by Vargas Rea. Describes the Nahuatl (mexica) pictographic forms of writing, with explanations of grammar and color images.
    - Historia Tolteca-Chichimeca, 1947.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Spanish translation of original Nahuatl text, though Nahuatl words are found throughout. Includes "Anales de Quauhtichan" and a prologue by Paul Kirchhoff. Typescripts with holograph corrections.
    - Illustrations, ca. 1930.; ca. 100 items. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Reprints of códice illustrations, depicting the Nahua before and after conquest. Printed by "Lit. Jules Desports. Inst. Imper. des Sourds-Muets." Loose leaves laid in a folder tied with string. See box 12 for oversize illustrations.
    - Indice Onomastico por Parrafos Personajes, Dioses, Pueblos y Tribus de la Nahuatl Historia Tolteca-Chichimeca, ca. 1947.; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Index to Historia Tolteca Chichimeca, plus three additional leaves. Typescript, bound with string. English and Spanish notes on Nahuatl text with holograph corrections. Pp. 129- 144.
    - Instituto Nacional Indigenista, 1955 November.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from Alfonso Caso to Angel Maria Garibay about translation of Anales of Tecamachalco and Códice Aubin. Bound typescript, 22 leaves.
    - Jiménez Moreno, Wigberto. Fray Bernardino de Sahagún y su obra, 1938.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Published in Mexico by D.F., P. Robredo. On the work of Fray Bernardino de Sahagún.
    - Leon, Nicolas. Códice Sierra: Traduccion al Español de su texto Nahuatl, 1927.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Essay on the Códice Sierra, with a Spanish translation of Nahuatl text, and analysis of images. Bound typescript.
    - Miscellaneous codice material, ca. 1940.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Nahuatl transcription of an untitled 1479 text ("XIII acatl xihuitl"), with reference to altepetl such as Amecameca, Ecatepec and Axayacatzin; bound typescript. Photostats of untitled, illustrated Nahuatl text. See box 12 for an oversize Spanish translation, with images, of the Códice de Santa María Asunción (1535?).
    - Notes, 1951.; 14 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)